Guide to the Benjamin Mordecai Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Benjamin Mordecai papers
1975-2005
YCAL MSS 790
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
19.96
(32 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 1 record album storage, 1 art
The majority of the collection consists of production programs, photographs, window cards, posters, and other publicity material relating to theatrical productions produced by Benjamin Mordecai at Yale Repertory Theatre and on Broadway. Award certificates, plaques and trophies he received as producer of Angels in America, The Piano Lesson, Seven Guitars, and other productions are included in the papers. In addition, there are legal and financial documents, correspondence, and other material relating to the production Golden Child, and computer disks containing Jitney production records. Audiovisual material includes videocassette and compact disc recordings of theatrical productions, Tony Award programs, and Benjamin Mordecai's memorial service, and a long-playing record album of Ma Rainey's Black Bottom.
Mordecai, Benjamin, 1944-2005
Hwang, David Henry, 1957- ( Golden child)
Kushner, Tony ( Angels in America)
Wilson, August ( Jitney)
Wilson, August ( August Wilson's The piano lesson)
Wilson, August ( Seven guitars)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sherry L. Mordecai, 2005-2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 19, 27-28 (sound and video recordings): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 35 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Benjamin Mordecai (1944-2005)
Benjamin Mordecai was born in New York City in 1944. He graduated from Buena Vista University in 1967, and received his Master of Arts degree from Eastern Michigan University in 1968. He was a founder of the Indiana Repertory Theatre in Indianapolis and the theater's producing director for eleven years (1971-1982). During his twenty-three year tenure at Yale University (1982-2005), Mordecai was associate dean and chair of the theater management program at the Yale School of Drama, and managing director of the Yale Repertory Theatre (1982 to 1993). Working closely with Yale School of Drama dean and Yale Repertory Theatre artistic director Lloyd Richards and the playwright August Wilson, Mordecai was the only person to have worked on the original productions of all ten plays in Wilson's cycle of plays about the African-American experience in the 20th century. Under his management, five of August Wilson's plays, as well as plays by Authol Fugard, Lee Blessing, and Eugene O'Neill moved from Yale to Broadway. In 1992, Mordecai founded his own producing and management firm, and was managing partner of Producers Four, a theatrical development and producing company. During his career he was involved in national tours and resident productions in the United States as well as productions in Great Britain, Russia, and Eastern Europe. He was the recipient of numerous awards for productions including three Tony Awards for Fences, The Piano Lesson, and Angels in America; Drama Desk Awards for Fences and The Piano Lesson; and the Olivier Award for Jitney. He also received the Robert Whitehead Award for outstanding commercial producing; two NAACP Theatre Awards; and a Special Achievement Award from the New England Theatre Conference. The Yale Repertory Theatre received a Tony for outstanding regional theatre in 1991, during Mordecai's tenure as the theater's managing director. He died in New Haven in 2005.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the collection consists of production programs, photographs, window cards, posters, and other publicity material relating to theatrical productions produced by Benjamin Mordecai. Certificates, plaques and trophies of awards he received as producer of Angels in America, The Piano Lesson, Seven Guitars, and other productions are included in the papers. In addition, there are legal and financial documents, correspondence, and other material relating to Golden Child, and computer disks containing various Jitney production records. Audiovisual material includes videocassette and compact disc recordings of theatrical productions, Tony Award programs, and Benjamin Mordecai's memorial service, and a record album of Ma Rainey's Black Bottom.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: I. October 2005 Acquisition, 1975-2005. II. May 2006 Acquisition, 1982-2005.
Theater -- Production and direction -- United States; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States; Born digital; Audiovisual materials; Theatrical posters; Theater programs; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States -- 20th Century; Mordecai, Benjamin, 1944-2005; Yale Repertory Theatre; Yale School of Drama
- October 2005 Acquisition, 1975-2005; 1; 11.17; (16 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 1 record album storage
  Arrangement
  Arranged by type of material.
  Scope and Contents
  Production programs, awards, window cards, posters, and a record album documenting theatrical productions produced or attended by Benjamin Mordecai.
  - Production Programs
    Consists of Playbill binders containing production programs from shows in New York and various other U.S. cities.
    - 1975 July - 1981 October (Box 1)
    - 1981 October - 1983 August (Box 1)
    - 1983 October - 1984 October (Box 1)
    - 1984 October- 1986 March (Box 1)
    - 1986 April - 1987 April (Box 2)
    - 1987 June - 1988 January (Box 2)
    - 1988 February - September (Box 2)
    - 1988 November - 1989 April (Box 2)
    - 1989 May - 1990 February (Box 3)
    - 1990 March - December (Box 3)
    - 1991 February- December (Box 3)
    - 1992 February - November (Box 3)
    - 1993 April - September (Box 4)
    - 1993 November - 1994 April (Box 4)
    - 1994 February - 1995 October (Box 4)
    - 1995 November - 1996 September (Box 4)
    - 1996 October - 1997 April (Box 5)
    - 1997 April - July (Box 5)
    - 1997 October - 1998 January (Box 5)
    - 1998 October - December (Box 5)
    - 1998 February - September (Box 6)
    - 1999 January- March (Box 6)
    - 1999 April - July (Box 6)
    - 1999 August - November (Box 6)
    - 1999 November - 2000 March (Box 7)
    - 2000 March - April (Box 7)
    - 2000 May - November (Box 7)
    - 2000 November - 2001 April (Box 7)
    - 2001 June - November (Box 8)
    - 2001 December - 2002 March (Box 8)
    - 2001 April - June (Box 8)
    - 2002 April - June (Box 8)
    - Unsorted, 1988-2004; 16 (Box 9)
  - Award Files
    - Playbill program for 12th Annual Abbott Award, 1996 (Box 10)
    - Playbill programs for Tony Awards, 1980-2001; 6 (Box 10)
    - W.I.T. membership plaque, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Buena Vista College plaque presented to Benjamin Mordecai, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Drama Desk Award nomination to Benjamin Mordecai for outstanding play producer for Angels in America, 1992-1993 (Box 10)
    - Tony nomination for best play producer for The Piano Lesson, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
    - Indianapolis City Council Resolution honoring Benjamin Mordecai, 1982 July 19 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Production Material
    - "Fences, A Play in Two Acts," by August Wilson, typescript copy, December 1984 (Box 10)
    - Program from Benjamin Mordecai's memorial service, 2005 (Box 10)
    - Three Sisters photographs of performance at Brooklyn Academy of Music, undated (Box 10)
    - Moon Over Miami by John Guare, typescript copy "Williamstown version", 1987 (Box 10)
    - King Hedley, printouts of photographs of cast and crew, 2001 June 28, undated (Box 10)
    - Seven Guitars promotional photographs, 1996 March 27 (Box 10)
    - Jitney, photograph of set, undated (Box 10)
  - Window Cards
    - Angels in America, 1993 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Blood Knot, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - BKLYN, the Musical, 2003 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - End Papers, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Fences, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Flower Drum Song, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - The Gate of Heaven, with signatures, 1996 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Gem of the Ocean, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Golden Child, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - The Harlem Nutcracker, 1998 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Jitney, signed with note by August Wilson, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Joe Turner's Come and Gone, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - The Kentucky Cycle, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - King Hedley II, signed with note from August Wilson, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - Love! Valor! Compassion!, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - Ma Rainey's Black Bottom, undated; 3 (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - "The O'Neill Plays", undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - The Piano Lesson, undated; 2 (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - Radio Golf, 2004-2005 (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - Redwood Curtain, 1993 (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - The Road to Mecca, undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - Seven Guitars, undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - The Silver River, undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - Sixteen Wounded, undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - Thunder Knocking on the Door, undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - Twilight: Los Angeles, 1992, signed by Anna Deavere Smith, 1994 (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - Two Trains Running, 1992; 2 (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - A Walk in the Woods, 1988 (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - Award Certificates
    - Angels in America, Drama Critics Circle, 1993 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Golden Child, Tony Award nomination, 1998 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - The Kentucky Cycle, Tony Award nomination, 1994 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - King Hedley II, Tony Award nomination, 2001 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - New York Drama Critics Circle Special Citation: Anna Deavere Smith, 1994 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - The Piano Lesson, New York Drama Critics Circle Award, 1990 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Seven Guitars, Tony Award nomination, 1996 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Twilight: Los Angeles, 1992, Tony Award nomination, 1994 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Two Trains Running, Tony Award nomination, 1992 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Two Trains Running, New York Drama Critics Circle Award, 1992 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Jitney, New York Drama Critics Circle Award, 2000 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Sagamore of the Wabish Award, 1991 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Beverly Hills/Hollywood NAACP Theatre Awards, Best Play/Producer for Two Trains Running, framed, 1992 December 14 (Box 15 (Oversize))
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Flower Drum Song, photographs, window cards, publicity material, 2001 (Box 16 (Oversize))
    - Small poster of New Yorker magazine cover, 1994 March 7 (Box 16 (Oversize))
  - Posters
    - Fences posters, 1985, 1986 (Box 17 (Broadside))
    - Jitney posters, 1999, 2001; 2 (Box 17 (Broadside))
    - Into the Woods poster from production at the Pushkin Theatre, Moscow, 1989 (Box 18 (Broadside))
  - Audiovisual Material
    - Ma Rainey's Black Bottom record album (Box 19 (Record Album Storage))
      Conditions Governing Access
      Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- May 2006 Acquisition, 1988-2005; 2; 8.79; (16 boxes) + 1 art
  Legal and financial records and promotional materials relating to Golden Child; Jitney scripts, prompt book, production notes, promotional material, photographs, and computer files; and photographs, audiocassettes, videocassettes, compact disks, awards and other material documenting theatrical productions produced by Benjamin Mordecai including plays by August Wilson and Anna Deveare Smith.
  - Golden Child Material
    - Contracts - music, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Contract - author, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Limited Partnership, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Final accountant's statements, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Contracts, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Company Business certificate, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Contracts: SCR/NYSF, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Jonathan Yap, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Limited partnership - Jujamcyn Theaters, 1997-1998 (Box 20)
    - Limited partnership - distribution (Box 20)
    - Joint Venture - Kennedy Center loan agreement, 1998 (Box 20)
    - East West Players loan agreement, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Limited partnership - Jon Platt, 1998 (Box 20)
    - David Henry Hwang - loan agreement, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Joint venture agreement between Benjamin Mordecai Productions and Intergalactic Entertainment LLC, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Joint Venture - Talia Shire loan agreement, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence with investors, 1997-1998 (Box 20)
    - Limited partnership - Dori Berinstein, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Checkbook and receipt, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Joint venture loan agreement reference memos, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Limited Partnership - John Kao, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Far East Bank, 2000-2003 (Box 20)
    - John Kao loan agreement, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Golden Child, the movie, 1999-2000 (Box 20)
    - Office - personal, 1999-2000 (Box 20)
    - Production programs, 1996-1998; 2 (Box 20)
    - T-shirt, undated (Box 20)
    - Press kits and production programs, undated (Box 20)
    - Performing Arts magazine issue and production programs, 1997 January, undated (Box 20)
    - Script and South Coast Repertory press kit (Box 20)
    - Promotional booklet for Singapore premiere, 1997-1998 (Box 20)
    - "Golden Child Focus Group Research Report", 1997 October (Box 20)
    - Press clippings (photocopies), undated (Box 20)
    - Photographs, candid, undated (Box 20)
  - Jitney Material
    - Ground plan, undated (Box 21)
    - Script and production program, undated (Box 21)
    - "Press pack", undated (Box 21)
    - Prompt book, undated (Box 21)
    - Scripts, 2 (Box 21)
    - Stage manager's calling script, 1999 (Box 21)
    - Production notes, undated; 2 (Box 21)
    - Prop notes, 1998 (Box 21)
    - Rehearsal notes, 2000 (Box 21)
    - Script with stage directions, undated (Box 21)
    - Photographs of props, undated (Box 21)
    - Production programs, undated (Box 21)
    - Promotional material, undated (Box 21)
    - Final script and promotional poster, undated (Box 21)
    - Lighting notes, undated (Box 21)
    - Window card, undated
  - Miscellaneous Material
    - Production programs for August Wilson plays, 1984-2002 (Box 22)
    - Seven Guitars, final production information [in binder], 1996 (Box 23)
    - Seven Guitars prompt book, undated (Box 24)
    - King Hedley, prop notebook, undated (Box 24)
    - King Hedley "master" (Box 24)
    - The Piano Lesson financial data, 1990-1991 (Box 24)
    - Unsorted production programs, 1982-2002; 9 (Box 25)
    - Tony Awards ceremony programs, 1994-2005; 3 (Box 25)
    - Photographs and ephemera, 2006, undated (Box 25)
    - Clippings, 1989 (Box 25)
    - stageblue publication celebrating anniversaries of the Yale Dramatic Association, Yale Repertory Theatre and Yale University, 2000 (Box 25)
    - Photographs of Mordecai with others, 1993, undated; 2 (Box 25)
    - Golden Child press kit, 1998 (Box 25)
    - Souvenir program for Flower Drum Song, undated (Box 25)
    - Production souvenirs, undated (Box 25)
    - Commemorative medal from the Samuel Dorsky Symposium, 1999 (Box 25)
  - Awards
    - Audelco Award for Jitney, 2000 November 20 (Box 26)
    - New England Theatre Conference special award for advancement in theatre, 1998 November 7 (Box 26)
    - Redwood Curtain opening night program cover [mounted], 1993 March 30 (Box 26)
    - Friends of New York Theatre Award nomination for Golden Child, 1998 (Box 26)
    - Drama Desk Award for Jitney, 2000 (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous award certificates, 2000-2001 (Box 26)
  - Audiovisual Material
    - Videocassettes
      - Jitney fight work with D. Leong, undated; YCALMSS790_0001; 1; 00:23:58 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339844)
      - Tony Awards, 2001; YCALMSS790_0002; 1; This tape appears to be recorded improperly. It was not digitized due to the snowy picture. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339851)
      - Unidentified, undated; YCALMSS790_0003; 1; 02:07:33 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339869)
        This tape includes ABC coverage of Princess Diana's funeral. It also includes Tony Awards coverage.
      - Golden Child/NY scenes, undated; YCALMSS790_0004; 00:16:15 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339877)
      - Golden Child by David Henry Hwang, directed by James Lapine, South Coast Repertory, undated; YCALMSS790_0005; 1; 00:15:15 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339885)
      - Golden Child, undated; YCALMSS790_0006; 1; 00:15:07 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339893)
      - Tony Awards, 1988; YCALMSS790_0007; 1; 02:18:17 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339901)
      - Tony Awards, 1998; YCALMSS790_0008; 1; 03:01:40 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339919)
      - August Wilson's King Hedley II, Virginia Theatre, undated; YCALMSS790_0009; 1; 00:20:59 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002102339927)
    - Compact disc
      - Flower Drum Song, compact disc, 2003 (Box 28)
  - Yale Repertory Theatre Lobby Exhibit Photographs
    - James Earl Jones in Fences, undated (Box 29 (Oversize))
    - Kimberleigh Burroughs, Cristal Coleman, Charles S. Dutton, Ed Hall in Joe Turner's Come and Gone, undated (Box 29 (Oversize))
    - Theresa Merrit in Ma Rainey's Black Bottom, undated (Box 29 (Oversize))
    - Lou Myers, Rocky Carroll, Samuel L. Jackson, Carl Gordon in The Piano Lesson, undated (Box 29 (Oversize))
    - James Earl Jones and Mary Alice in Fences, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
    - Lou Criscuolo, Robert Judd, Joe Seneca, Theresa Merritt, and Richard M. Davidson in Ma Rainey's Black Bottom, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
    - Charles S. Dutton in The Piano Lesson, with caption, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
    - Lou Myers, Rocky Carroll, Samuel L. Jackson, and Carl Gordon in The Piano Lesson, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
    - Viola Davis in Seven Guitars, with caption, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
    - Lawrence Fishburne and Ella Joyce in Two Trains Running, with caption, undated (Box 31 (Oversize))
    - "Playwright August Wilson at work" with caption, undated (Box 31 (Oversize))
    - Playwright August Wilson and director Lloyd Richards, undated (Box 31 (Oversize))
  - Window Cards
    - Flower Drum Song, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - Golden Child, 1998 (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - Harlem Nutcracker "Break a leg!", 1998 December 22 (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - Jitney, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - Joe Turner's Come and Gone, 1998 (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - King Hedley II, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - Ma Rainey's Black Bottom, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - The Piano Lesson, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - Seven Guitars, 1995-1996 (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - Two Trains Running, 1992 (Box 32 (Oversize))
  - Oversize
    - Reproduction of signature of August Wilson, mounted (Box 33 (Oversize))
    - Awards
      - Twilight: Los Angeles, 1992 opening night program [mounted], 1994 (Box 34 (Oversize))
      - Beverly Hills/Hollywood NAACP Theatre Awards, Best Play/Producer for The Piano Lesson, framed, 1991 December 9 (Box 34 (Oversize))
  - Computer media
    - Eleven computer disks relating to Jitney
      Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - 1 Copy MAC FORMAT Goodman Script & Forms, 2006-ycal-31-0001; 1 (Box 35)
        Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - ORIG. The Theatre Goodman 99 TECH DOCUMENTS JITNEY, 2006-ycal-31-0002; 1 (Box 35)
      - 2 JITNEY GOODMAN 99 ORIG., 2006-ycal-31-0003; 1 (Box 35)
      - OBSESSION 600 JITNEY-NYC, 2006-ycal-31-0004; 1 (Box 35)
      - JITNEY O 2R BACK UP, 2006-ycal-31-0005; 1 (Box 35)
      - 3 Copy Mac Format Goodman Tech Documents, 2006-ycal-31-0006; 1 (Box 35)
      - 2 copy MAC FORMAT Goodman 99, 2006-ycal-31-0007; 1 (Box 35)
      - 1 copy JITNEY 7/99 Script + forms To MaRK TAPER (From Goodman), 2006-ycal-31-0008; 1 (Box 35)
      - 3 Copy Goodman 99 TECH DOCUMENTS JITNEY., 2006-ycal-31-0009; 1 (Box 35)
      - 2 Copy JITNEY Goodman 99, 2006-ycal-31-0010; 1 (Box 35)
      - 1 ORIG. JITNEY 7/99 SCRIPT + FORMS TO MARK TAPER, 2006-ycal-31-0011; 1 (Box 35)
    - Benjamin Mordecai's memorial service on DVD, 2005
      - REMEMBERING BEN A Tribute to the Life and Work of Benjamin Mordecai December 10, 1944 - May 8, 2005, 2006-ycal-31-0012; 1 (Box 35)
  - Objects
    - King Hedley machete, mounted (Box 36 (Art))
      Includes plate with the following inscription: "'This is the machete of the 'Conquering Lion of Judea,' Stool Pigeon, King Hedley II: Act II, Scene 1."